84. The plane of jars. Laos, or Lao PDR, is a calm green oasis between other bigger,
faster, and stronger nations. Near the center of this quiet country is a quiet mystery,
the beautiful, unexplainable plane of jars. The plane of jars refers to more than 90 areas
within Laos' Xian Quang Province. The sites are mostly the same. There are the green rolling
hills of Lao, there are mountains in the distance, in the fields sunk into the grass or tipped
onto their sides are many giant jars. The jars seem to have lids, though the lids have
all disappeared over the centuries. There are also a few flat stone plates carved with
animals. Why were large, heavy stone jars, some larger than a man and with thick, rough sides,
scattered across the fields in this place? There are local legends and different scientific
theories. Local legend holds that the jars stole Lao Lao, rice whiskey for a group of giants who
lived there. According to that legend, the jars aren't made of stone but clay and were fired in
a huge cave oven. Most current experts seem to think the jars were for funerals to hold the
ashes of the dead. It's also possible the jars were used to store rainwater for travelers. There
is no indication of who built them or why. We only have a rough idea of when. The Iron Age, 500 BC
to AD 500 BC. It seems appropriate to have this quiet mystery in this quiet country. The jars,
perhaps, reflect the beauty of the country. Simple, natural, rough, and charming.